Guide to the Nathan Judson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nathan Judson papers
1837-1950
1880-1930
WA MSS S-2695
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.71
(7 boxes)
The papers document the business and personal life of Nathan Judson, his brother James B. Judson, and his nephews Wilber, Lowell, and Paul. Correspondence and financial records document the activity of the firms Judson, Wiley & Judson and Judson Brothers in late nineteenth-century and early twentieth-century Michigan, and the Judson Brothers fruit growing business in Kinderhook, New York. Correspondence documents the buying and selling of Michigan real estate, mining investments in various western states and Mexico (including the Buck Eye Mining Company in Basin, Montana and the Sierra Mining Company in Ocampo, Chihuahua, Mexico), and the horticulture business in the Hudson Valley of New York State in the 1910s and 1920s. Other than correspondence, the collection includes fragmentary financial records (including bank records and cancelled checks) and real estate documents (including deeds and abstracts to holdings in Michigan).
Judson, Nathan
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Tom Stanford on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Nathan Judson
Nathan Judson was a real estate dealer in Lansing, Michigan. Together with his brother James B. Judson, he ran the firms Judson, Wiley & Judson, and Judson Brothers. In addition to buying and selling Michigan real estate, he invested in gold mines, including the Buck Eye Mining Company in Basin, Montana. After the death of James, he supported the education of his three nephews Wilber, Lowell, and Paul Judson. Wilber travelled extensively in the Western United States and in Mexico to investigate mining prospects on behalf of his uncle. Wilber worked at several mines, including the Buck Eye Mine in Basin, Montana (1902-1903), an unidentified mine in Panama (1905), and the Sierra Mining Company in Ocampo, Chihuahua, Mexico (1911). Paul and Lowell founded the Judson Brothers fruit growing business in Kinderhook, New York.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the business and personal life of Nathan Judson, his brother James B. Judson, and his nephews Wilber, Lowell, and Paul. Correspondence and financial records document the activity of the firms Judson, Wiley & Judson and Judson Brothers, in late nineteenth-century and early twentieth-century Michigan. Correspondence documents the buying and selling of Michigan real estate, mining investments in various western states and Mexico (including the Buck Eye Mining Company in Basin, Montana and the Sierra Mining Company in Ocampo, Chihuahua, Mexico), and the horticulture business in the Hudson Valley of New York State in the 1910s and 1920s. Other than correspondence, the collection includes fragmentary financial records (including bank records and cancelled cheques) and real estate documents (including deeds and abstracts to holdings in Michigan).
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Correspondence, 1880-1950. II. Financial and Real Estate Records, 1837-1902.
Gold mines and mining -- Mexico; Gold mines and mining -- Montana; Horticulture -- New York (State); Land titles -- Michigan; Real estate agents -- Michigan; Real property -- Michigan; Mexico -- Gold discoveries; Montana -- Gold discoveries; Real estate agents -- Michigan; Judson, James B.; Judson, Lowell; Judson, Nathan; Judson, Paul; Judson, Wilber; Buck Eye Mining Company; Judson Brothers; Judson, Wiley & Judson; Sierra Mining Company
- Correspondence, 1880-1950; Series I; 1.88; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Early correspondence (before 1911) relates chiefly to Michigan real estate and includes letters sent to landowners, often in Eastern states, making offers on their holdings in Michigan. Correspondence from the 1900s and 1910s includes documentation of the Judsons' involvement in mining ventures. Much of the later correspondence relates to Nathan Judson's business and personal relationships with his three nephews: Wilber, Lowell, and Paul Judson.
  - Correspondence, 1880-1897 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Correspondence, 1898-1905 (Box 2, Folder 6-11)
  - Correspondence, 1906-1922 (Box 3, Folder 12-18)
  - Correspondence, 1923-1945 (Box 4, Folder 19-22)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 23-24)
  - Other papers found with correspondence, 1899-1950 (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
- Financial and Real Estate Records, 1837-1902; Series II; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Organized into two files by type of material: Real estate records, and Financial records.
  Real estate records include deeds and abstracts to lands purchased by Nathan Judson, Judson Brothers, and Judson, Wiley & Judson. Financial records consist chiefly of cancelled checks drawn on the Judson Brothers accounts.
  - Real estate records, including deeds, 1837-1900 (Box 6, Folder 27-31)
  - Financial records, chiefly checks and bank records, 1898-1902 (Box 7, Folder 32-36)